Guide to the William E. Mead Papers, 1880 - 1944
William E. Mead Papers, 1880 - 1944
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Mead, William Edward, 1860-1949.
1000-94
4.5
9
William E. Mead was an alumnus of Wesleyan University and served as professor at the school, in addition to teaching and administration at high schools. His wife, Kate Mead Hurd, was a physician and author. The Meads travelled extensively in Europe and other parts of the world.
The William E. Mead papers include diaries recording his life and travels, correspondence and other materials removed from the diaries, and journals and a photograph album of a trip to Iceland in 1891.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Unknown. It appears that the papers probably came to Wesleyan shortly after Mead’s death in 1949 because there was a note that papers could not be examined until 1974, which would be 25 years after his death. Mead bequeathed his personal library of almost 4,000 volumes to the Wesleyan Library. He had donated 200 volumes to the Library in 1927.
Biographical Note
William Edward Mead was born on October 25, 1860 in Gallupville, New York. His father, Merritt B. Mead was a Methodist minister. He attended Wesleyan and graduated with the Class of 1881 with special honors in English literature. He stayed at Wesleyan as a graduate student and assistant librarian until 1882 when he became the associate principal of Ansonia high school in Ansonia, Connecticut. In 1884, he returned to Wesleyan as assistant in rhetoric and also teaching history at the Normal School in New Britain. The following year, Mead became principal of a high school in Troy, New York. He went abroad to study for the next five years in Germany, Paris, and London. While abroad, he became acquainted with Kate Hurd who was traveling for pleasure. Mead returned to Wesleyan in 1890 as Associate Professor of English, became full professor in 1893, and emeritus in 1925. A listing of many of Mead’s many publications can be found by searching the Wesleyan Library Catalog and the separate card files of faculty and alumni publications in Special Collections and Archives.
Kate Campbell Hurd was the daughter of Dr. Hurd of Newburyport, Massachusetts. She was born on April 6, 1867 in Danville, Quebec, Canada, and graduated from the Woman’s Medical College of Pennsylvania in 1888. She continued her medical studies at New England Hospital in Boston and at various universities in Europe and the Johns Hopkins Medical School. From 1890-93, she was medical director at the Bryn Mawr School in Baltimore.
William Mead married Kate Hurd on June 23, 1893. After their wedding, they went on a trip to Norway and Europe. They took up residence in Middletown and stayed until 1929 when they moved to Sunnymede, a house overlooking the Connecticut River, in Haddam. A photograph of the house appears in the 1932 correspondence folder (Series II, Box 9, folder 49). The Meads traveled extensively throughout the world, especially after Professor Mead’s retirement from Wesleyan in 1925.
Kate Hurd Mead died at her home of a heart attack while assisting a groundskeeper who had collapsed while fighting a brush fire on the Mead estate. At the time of her death on January 1, 1941, at age 73, Kate was a widely known medical author and practicing physician. She was the first woman doctor in Middletown. She had published A History of Women in Medicine, covering ancient times through the 18th century. A second volume was at the printers, and a third volume was almost finished.
Professor Mead died on July 12, 1949 at Middlesex Hospital in Middletown. He was 88. The Meads had no children.
Collection Overview
The Mead Papers consist primarily of diaries, with one volume for each year from 1880 to 1944, with the exception of 1887 and 1922 for which no volumes exist. These volumes are arranged chronologically in Series I, Boxes 1-8, folders 1-30.
Mead inserted, pasted, or paper-clipped correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other such items into his diaries. Until about 1920, few such items appeared and they have usually been left in place, especially if the item was small and related to the diary entry for a particular day. After 1920, Mead inserted more things into the front or back covers of the diary. These loose items, especially folded correspondence, programs, and clippings, were removed from the diary and placed in Series II in chronological order.
For 1891, the year that Mead traveled to Iceland, there is one separate two-volume journal and one photograph album covering the period 1891 July 8 to September 1. These items are housed in Series III, Box 9, folders 58-60. For the period before and after the Iceland trip in 1891, there is an 1891 diary housed in Series I, Box 1, folder 4. The diaries provide insight into the daily life style of a well-established Wesleyan faculty member. Entries relate to weather, visitors and visiting, travel, and reading. Some entries mention his wife, but for the most part, they are concerned with what William did. When traveling, many of the entries give a location with the date.
The Mead diaries are noteworthy for recording the amount of traveling that Mead did both before he married Kate, and throughout their married years, especially in the 1920s and 1930s. In a May 1922 article for the Wesleyan Alumnus, Mead writes about their travels to Paris, Rome, Cairo, and Jerusalem. They were again on a world tour after Meads retirement from Wesleyan in 1925. This tour lasted about five years. They spent much of 1926 touring Europe, London, Spain, Francis, Tunis. An article in the December 1926 issue of the Wesleyan Alumnus mentions that Professor and Mrs. Mead have postponed their visit to China. (The Meads did not travel to China until 1936.) In 1927, they journeyed to the Canary Islands, Naples, Pompeii, Athens, Tripoli. In 1928, they were in Rangoon, Bombay, Athens; and 1929 London, Paris Rome. They returned home to Haddam on October 4, 1929. Another item of note that appear in the collection is a ten page typescript by Kate, dated May 30, 1932, (Box 8, folder 49) giving an account of a trip soth to New Orleans. Diaries entries give location where the entry is written: Haddam, at sea, etc. Traveling continued until Kate’s death.
In 1936, the Meads traveled to China. They began their journey from Connecticut to China on January 4 when they drove from Haddam to New Haven and took a train to New York. By the morning of January 7, they crossed the Mexican border at the Rio Grande at Laredo. On January 8, they were in Mexico City, and on the 24th they boarded the President Hoover in San Francisco, and arrived in Honolulu on the 29th. On the 28th of February the Meads were in Shanghai where they were met by John McGregor Gibb, Wesleyan Class of 1904, who was in the exporting business. The Meads were in Canton in early March. They had dinner with E.K. Smith, Wesleyan Class of 1895, on March 23 and visited the Great Wall on March 24. William’s diary provides a daily record of the China trip from the time he and Kate left Haddam in January until they returned home to Haddam on May 17.
The summer of 1937 found the Meads in London, Paris and Amsterdam. In April 1938, William broke his hip. There was not much traveling until May 1939 when they drove cross country. In July 1940 through August, the Meads drove to Canada and Nova Scotia. William notes in his diary that he is now 80 years old.
Although Mead was associate principal of Ansonia high school for only two years, he seemed to maintain contact and interest in the school. In the correspondence files, there is a copy of a graduation program for March 28, 1884 and photograph of students and teachers dated 1883 (Series II, Box 8, folder 31). An article about the retirement of Mary E. Lathrop as Librarian of Derby High School, from the Ansonia Evening Sentinel, dated July 29, 1932, is filed in the 1932 correspondence folder (Series II, Box 9, folder 49). The 1933 folder (Series II, Box 9, folder 50) contains an article from The Observer titled, “1933 Looks Back to 1883,” by Lois Davidson about the first class to graduate Ansonia High School in 1883 that mentions Mead.
The collections contains some family correspondence especially with Kate’s sister, Mabeth Hurd Paige. Mabeth was a member of the Minnesota state legislature. Her husband, James Paige, died on February 4, 1940. Mabeth had two daughters, Emma and Elizabeth. Kate’s brother, Randolph Campbell Hurd (1872-1956) was a member of the Wesleyan Class of 1895, but left school in his sophomore year. He received an M.D. degree from Harvard in 1897.
Kate Mead seemed to forsee her death. In November 1940, on a trip to New York with her sister, Mabeth Hurd Paige, Kate discusses how William should be cared for in the event of her death. Shortly after Kate’s death, Mabeth typed up a document outlining Kate’s wishes that William signed. This contract appears near the front cover of the 194l diary. With Kate’s death, William appeared to decline quickly. His handwriting deteriorated, entries became shorter, and he did not travel or want travel. His last diary entry is for April 5, 1944, five years before his death: Haddam Overcast... ? Read as usual. William died in 1949 at the age of 88.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: Diaries, Correspondence, and Icelandic Journals.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Mead, William Edward, 1860-1949.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Hurd-Mead, Kate Campbell, 1867-1941.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Alumni and alumnae.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Iceland--Pictorial works.; Diaries.; Travel writing.; Photographs.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Diaries
  - 1880-1882 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1883-1885 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1886; 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1890-1892 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1893-1894 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1895-1896 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1897-1898 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1899-1900 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1901-1902 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1905-1906 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1907-1908 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1909-1910 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1911-1912 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 1915-1916 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 1917-1918 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 1919-1920 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 1921, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - 1926-1927 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - 1936-1937 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - 1944 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Ansonia High School, 1883 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Judson, H.P., October 28, 1890 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Hurd, Mabeth, April 8 and May 22, 1891 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Hurd, S.E.C., January 10 and May 12, 1891 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - King of Norway photograph by Max Behrends, undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous from diary, 1917-1918 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Miscellanous and clippings, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Aunt Julia, May 21, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Keller, Sara B., March 11, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, March-December, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, photo, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1926 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Hazen, Edward W., Estate, August 24, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Family correspondence, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Photos removed from 1939 diary, 1921, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous and travel account, 1932 (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - Family correspondence, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, photos, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Paige, James obituary, February 4, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Mead, Kate Hurd obituary, January 1, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Paige, Mabeth; Terry, Flora, May 20 and December 15, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 57)
- Series III: Icelandic Journals
  - Iceland Journal, July 8-August 10, 1891 (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Iceland Journal, August 15-September 1, 1891 (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Photograph album of Iceland, 1891 (Box 9, Folder 60)